- The Hooks were first introduced in 2018.
They have been a new additions
to the React library since the version 16.8.
The Hooks give developers the ability
to create stateful components,
and use other React features
without having to write a class.
In other words, Hooks are functions
that lets you hook into the React states
and lifecycle features from a function components.
And so the React API provides
with a few built-in hooks like useState.
useState is a React Hook that lets you add
and store local state variables in a components.
And this is how the syntax looks like.
Whenever you call useState in a component,
it returns an array, with first,
a variable and a function, to update the state.
A new state can take a value as a parameter
of any type to set an initial value.
In this module, we cover how to manage the state effectively
in a React project by using the React built-in Hooks.
The next example is a math game
where users must mentally calculate
the results of two values added together.
To get started, we start in
your virtual machine, in Codespaces.
As a reminder, this course is created
using GitHub Codespaces, which is a code editor
available online and directly integrated into GitHub.
And so, the first time that you open up Codespaces,
it might take a few minutes to start a new virtual machine.
And once this is ready,
you will enter the online code editor.
Now, we navigate to our first example
inside the exercise-files.
You're going to find our first project about useState.
Inside, you're going to find a starter project.
So I'm going to open the terminal.
And I'm going to navigate to the exercise-files.
And then to our first project about the Hook useState,
and navigate to the starter project.
And you want to make sure that you install the dependencies
by running npm-install, or npm i for shorts.
And then npm starts.
To start the project, that's going to open
a new window in the browser.
And here we go.
So this is how our starter project looks like.
So this is a basic application
where users can calculate two values.
So first, you want to click on this button
to generate two values.
And then, in this input you will add up.
You will first add up the two together,
and then enter the answer in this input.
So let's go back to the source code.
We're going to look at the starter project.
You're going to see that we already have some boilerplate code.
With first, this function, generateRandomValues,
that we're going to use to generate two random values.
And this function is going to run each time
that you click on this button.
But the goal here is to keep track of these values.
So for that, we're going to use useState.
We're going to define local state variables.
First, we want to make sure that we add
to the scope of this project.
This module useState that we're going to import
from the React module.
So I'm going to remove the commands like this.
And next, I'm going to be able to define local state variables.
So for now, I have already defined,
as part of this starter projects,
this local state variables.
So we're going to be able to keep track
of these values by running setValues.
And it's going to be random1
for the first random value, and random2.
And we would like to do the same
for the value that we enter
inside this input by the user.
So let's go back, and you're going to find inside the project,
this text input right here.
So for now, we are just learning out the value.
But instead, you want to keep track of the value,
which is entered by the user.
So for that, I'm going to define
another local state variable right below.
And I'm going to name this one input, and then setInput.
That's the function that we use to update.
And then useState.
And I'm going to define a default value as 0.
And next, let's go back to the text input
and replace this with setInput.
And let's try that. Let's go back to the browser.
We're going to refresh and also open the console.
And also the tab that corresponds
to the React Developer Tools,
and highlights our root component, which is app.
And here, you see that you have visible,
the two local state variables.
We're going to be able to see. We're going to keep an eye on it.
And each time that you click on this button,
you're going to be able to see that
now we have two values that are randomly generated.
So let's try again.
You're going to see that it's going to change.
And then we're going to add up the two together.
And that should add up to 37.
But, what we would like also,
is to see those two values visible right here.
So we're going to make a few changes,
and complete the source code. Go back right here.
You're going to find here,
that we have hardcoded those two values 0.
So we're going to replace
with those local state variables, which are values.
We're going to refer to values, then random1.
And the second one will be values.random2.
And the next time that we click on this button,
we're going to be able to see that now,
we're going to see the two values. So let me refresh first.
I'm going to close the console.
Here we go. So now you can see that
we have those two values generated.
And next time, what we want is to see
if the value that we enter in this input matches
the two values here added together.
The goal in this game is to calculate
and submit the correct value after adding up
the two values that we have randomly generated.
For that purpose, we have implemented useState,
the useState Hook.
Coming next, we want to check if there is a match
between the two random values and the user inputs.
We want to see how to manage the state
and also apply side effects based on the state change.
So I will introduce you to another Hook next,
which is useEffects.